<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Go - Tag - Blog of the Dad</title>
        <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/tags/go/</link>
        <description>Go - Tag - Blog of the Dad</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 18:21:01 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/tags/go/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>All Different Variants</title>
    <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/all-different-variants/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 18:21:01 -0800</pubDate><author>
        <name>Andrei</name>
    </author><guid>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/all-different-variants/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/spongebob-crossed-eyes.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div>In the earlier posts I&rsquo;ve described some of the basic ideas behind CSPs:
how the problems are represented using variables and constraints, how the solver searches for a solution by building up the search tree, how heuristics guide the search, and how constraint propagation helps eliminate parts of the search space that will not contain solutions. In this post I will look at how modeling the problem itself can have a significant influence on how quickly the solver is able to find a solution.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Constraint Propagation</title>
    <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/constraint-propagation/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 15:59:06 -0700</pubDate><author>
        <name>Andrei</name>
    </author><guid>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/constraint-propagation/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/4q-prop.svg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>Constraint propagation is one of the key mechanisms that allows constructive search to efficiently explore huge search spaces. It does so by applying constraints whenever search state changes to remove parts of search space that cannot contain solutions.</p>
<p>In this post I&rsquo;ll cover two constraint propagation techniques: forward checking and arc consistency. As these techniques apply to variables&rsquo; live domains, I&rsquo;ll start by defining what that is first, and then dive into constraint propagation itself.</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Search Algo in Go</title>
    <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/search-algo-in-go/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 10:24:10 -0700</pubDate><author>
        <name>Andrei</name>
    </author><guid>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/search-algo-in-go/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My previous couple of posts talked about <a href="https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/solver-intro/" rel="">what the solver does (solves CSPs)</a>, <a href="https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/solver-basics/" rel="">how to model a problem as a CSP, and how the search tree is built</a> as the solver searches for a solution. In this post I will expand on the details of search by outlining the key data structures and bits of code. The backend is written in <a href="https://go.dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Go lang</a>, and so are all of the code snippets here.</p>]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
