
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Tags on Blog of the Dad</title>
   <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/tags/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Tags on Blog of the Dad</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en-us</language>
   
       <atom:link href="https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/tags/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Why tho</title>
       <link>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/why-tho/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 21:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/posts/why-tho/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.dawnofthe.dad/y-tho.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Oblig meme&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and why?&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, the &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://dawnofthe.dad&#34;&gt;Dawn of the Dad&lt;/a&gt; is basically the 2 solvers: one for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dawnofthe.dad/sudoku&#34;&gt;sudoku&lt;/a&gt;, and another for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dawnofthe.dad/sudoku&#34;&gt;building crosswords&lt;/a&gt;. The first is largely complete, so most of my time now is dedicated to beefing up the crossword builder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now the &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; build the site and why ramble in this blog?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The site is my excuse to write some code, both to stay sharp and because I like doing it, solve some algorithmically interesting problems, and revisit some of the neat things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about back in grad school. Originally, this spun off as a yet-another-rewrite of a general-purpose &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constraint_satisfaction_problem&#34;&gt;CSP&lt;/a&gt; solver, which then led to adding fairly ad hoc visualization, which led to building a web server, hacking up a websocket protocol, glueing it all together and finally hosting it on Google Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The blog is largely meant to capture some of the interesting things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned along the way, like tuning / optimizing the solver and dealing with the hug of death I got from that one time my site briefly hit the front page of &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/news&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;post-frequency&#34;&gt;Post frequency&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll probably end up writing a bunch of posts relatively quickly at first, as I&amp;rsquo;m catching up on a year&amp;rsquo;s worth of potentially interesting things to write down, before I forget them. Once I do, I expect things to slow down a fair bit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
